This year, Germany is celebrating
في هذا العام، تحتفل ألمانيا
the 25th anniversary of the peaceful revolution
بالذكرى الـ25 للثورة السلمية
in East Germany.
في ألمانيا الشرقية.
In 1989, the Communist regime was moved away,
في 1989، أُخرج النظام الشيوعي،
the Berlin Wall came down, and one year later,
سقط جدار برلين، وبعد عام،
the German Democratic Republic, the GDR,
وحِّدت الجمهورية الألمانية الديموقراطية (GDR)
in the East was unified
في الشرق مع
with the Federal Republic of Germany in the West
الجمهورية الألمانية الفدرالية في الغرب
to found today's Germany.
لتأسيس ألمانيا كما هي اليوم.
Among many other things, Germany inherited
من ضمن أمور أخرى، ورثت ألمانيا
the archives of the East German secret police,
أرشيفات الشرطة السرية لألمانيا الشرقية،
known as the Stasi.
المعروفة بالستاسي.
Only two years after its dissolution,
بعد عامين فقط من حلّها،
its documents were opened to the public,
فتحت وثائقها للعامة،
and historians such as me started
ومؤرخون مثلي بدؤوا
to study these documents
بدراسة هذه الوثائق
to learn more about how the GDR surveillance state
لمعرفة المزيد عن آلية عمل دولة الرقابة
functioned.
الجمهورية الألمانية الديموقراطية.
Perhaps you have watched the movie
قد تكون شاهدت فيلم
"The Lives of Others."
"حياة الآخرين".
This movie made the Stasi known worldwide,
جعل هذا الفيلم الستاسي مشهورة عالميًا،
and as we live in an age where words
وحيث أننا نعيش في عصر حيث كلمات
such as "surveillance" or "wiretapping"
مثل "رقابة" أو "تنصت"
are on the front pages of newspapers,
تظهر على وجه الجرائد،
I would like to speak about how the Stasi
أود أن أتحدث عن كيف
really worked.
عمل الستاسي في الحقيقة.
At the beginning, let's have a short look
في البداية، فلنلق نظرة قصيرة
at the history of the Stasi,
على تاريخ الستاسي،
because it's really important for understanding
لأنها مهمة فعلًا لفهم
its self-conception.
تصورها لذاتها.
Its origins are located in Russia.
تقع أصولها في روسيا.
In 1917, the Russian Communists founded
في 1917، أسس الشيوعيون الروس
the Emergency Commission for Combating
لجنة الطوارئ لمكافحة
Counter-Revolution and Sabotage,
الثورة المضادة والتخريب
shortly Cheka.
أو "الشيكا" باختصار.
It was led by Felix Dzerzhinsky.
كان قائدها فيلكس دزيرجنسكي.
The Cheka was an instrument of the Communists
كانت الشيكا أداة الشيوعيين
to establish their regime by terrorizing the population
ليؤسسوا نظامهم عبر إرهاب الشعب
and executing their enemies.
وإعدام أعدائهم.
It evolved later into the well-known KGB.
تطورت لاحقًا للـKGB المعروف اليوم.
The Cheka was the idol of the Stasi officers.
كانت الشيكا قدوة ضباط الستاسي.
They called themselves Chekists,
سموا أنفسهم شيكيين،
and even the emblem was very similar,
وحتى شعارهم كان مشابهًا جدًا،
as you can see here.
كما ترون هنا.
In fact, the secret police of Russia
في الحقيقة، كانت الشرطة السرية الروسية
was the creator and instructor of the Stasi.
الخالق والمعلم للستاسي.
When the Red Army occupied East Germany in 1945,
حين احتل الجيش الأحمر ألمانيا الشرقية في 1945،
it immediately expanded there,
توسعت مباشرة هناك
and soon it started to train the German Communists
وسريعًا بدأت بتدريب الشيوعيين الألمان
to build up their own secret police.
ليكوّنوا شرطة سرية خاصة بهم.
By the way, in this hall where we are now,
على فكرة، في هذه القاعة حيث نحن الآن
the ruling party of the GDR was founded in 1946.
تأسس الحزب الحاكم للـGDR عام 1946،
Five years later, the Stasi was established,
بعد خمس سنين، تأسست الستاسي،
and step by step, the dirty job of oppression
وخطوة بخطوة، العمل القذر القمعي
was handed over to it.
سلّم لها.
For instance, the central jail
على سبيل المثال، السجن المركزي
for political prisoners,
للسجناء السياسيين،
which was established by the Russians,
والذي أسسه الروس
was taken over by the Stasi
سيطر عليه الستاسي
and used until the end of Communism.
واستخدم حتى نهاية الشيوعية.
You see it here.
ترونه هنا.
At the beginning, every important step
في البداية، كل خطوة هامة
took place under the attendance of the Russians.
أخذت تحت حضور الروس.
But the Germans are known to be very effective,
لكن الألمان معروفون لكفاءتهم،
so the Stasi grew very quickly,
لذا كبر الستاسي بسرعة،
and already in 1953, it had more employees
وحتى في 1953، كان لديها موظفون أكثر
than the Gestapo had,
مما كان لدى الجستابو،
the secret police of Nazi Germany.
الشرطة السرية لألمانيا النازية.
The number doubled in each decade.
تضاعف العدد كل عقد.
In 1989, more than 90,000 employees
في 1989، أكثر من 90 ألف موظف
worked for the Stasi.
عملوا للستاسي.
This meant that one employee
عنى ذلك أن كل موظف
was responsible for 180 inhabitants,
كان مسؤولًا عن 180 ساكن،
which was really unique in the world.
وهو أمر مميز في العالم.
At the top of this tremendous apparatus,
على رأس هذا الجهاز الضخم،
there was one man, Erich Mielke.
كان هناك رجل واحد، إريخ ميلك.
He ruled the Ministry of State Security
حكم وزارة أمن الدولة
for more than 30 years.
لأكثر من 30 عامًا.
He was a scrupulous functionary —
كان موظفًا دقيقًا -
in his past, he killed two policemen
في ماضيه، قتل شرطيين
not far away from here —
ليس بعيدًا من هنا -
who in fact personalized the Stasi.
وقام بالفعل بإضفاء طابع شخصي للستاسي.
But what was so exceptional about the Stasi?
ولكن ما الذي كان استثنائيًا عن الستاسي؟
Foremost, it was its enormous power,
في البداية، كانت قوة ضخمة،
because it united different functions
لأنها وحدت أدوارًا مختلفة
in one organization.
تحت منظمة واحدة.
First of all, the Stasi
أولًا، كانت الستاسي
was an intelligence service.
خدمة استخباراتية.
It used all the imaginable instruments
سخرت كل الأدوات الممكن تخيلها
for getting information secretly,
للحصول على المعلومات سريًا،
such as informers, or tapping phones,
مثل العملاء، أو التنصت على الهواتف،
as you can see it on the picture here.
كما ترون في الصورة هنا.
And it was not only active in East Germany,
ولم تكن نشطة في ألمانيا الشرقية وحسب،
but all over the world.
بل حول كل العالم.
Secondly, the Stasi was a secret police.
ثانيا، كانت الستاسي شرطة سرية.
It could stop people on the street
كانت تستطيع إيقاف الناس في الشارع
and arrest them in its own prisons.
وإلقاء القبض عليهم في سجونها.
Thirdly, the Stasi worked
ثالثًا، عملت الستاسي
as a kind of public prosecutor.
كمدعٍ عام من نوع ما.
It had the right to open preliminary investigations
كان لديها الحق لبدء تحقيقات تمهيدية
and to interrogate people officially.
ولاستجواب الناس رسميًا.
Last but not least,
أخيرًا وليس آخرًا،
the Stasi had its own armed forces.
كان للستاسي قواتها المسلحة الخاصة.
More than 11,000 soldiers were serving
أكثر من 11 ألف جندي عملوا
in its so-called Guards Regiment.
في ما تسميه كتيبة الحرس الخاصة بها.
It was founded to crash down protests and uprisings.
أسست لتعطيل المظاهرات والثورات
Due to this concentration of power,
بسبب هذا التركيز للسلطة،
the Stasi was called a state in the state.
سميت الستاسي دولة ضمن دولة.
But let's look in more and more detail
لكن لننظر بمزيد من التفصيل
at the tools of the Stasi.
على أدوات الستاسي.
Please keep in mind that at that time
خذوا في الاعتبار أن ذاك الوقت
the web and smartphones were not yet invented.
لم تخترع الشبكة ولا الجوالات الذكية.
Of course, the Stasi used all kinds
بالتأكيد، استخدمت الستاسي كل أنواع
of technical instruments to survey people.
الأدوات التقنية لتفقد الناس.
Telephones were wiretapped,
تُنصِّتَ على الهواتف،
including the phone of the German chancellor in the West,
من ضمنها هاتف مستشار ألمانيا في الغرب،
and often also the apartments.
وكثيرًا حتى الشقق.
Every day, 90,000 letters were being opened
في كل يوم يتم فتح 90 ألف رسالة
by these machines.
من قبل هذه الآلات.
The Stasi also shadowed tens of thousands of people
الستاسي أيضًا تتبعت عشرات آلاف الناس
using specially trained agents and secret cameras
باستخدام عملاء مدربين وكاميرات سرية
to document every step one took.
لتوثيق كل خطوة يأخذها الشخص.
In this picture, you can see me
في هذه الصورة، تستطيعون رؤيتي
as a young man just in front of this building
كشابٍّ أمام هذا المبنى
where we are now, photographed by a Stasi agent.
حيث نحن الآن، مصورة من قبل عميل للستاسي.
The Stasi even collected the smell of people.
قامت الستاسي حتى بجمع روائح الناس.
It stored samples of it in closed jars
خزنت عينات في عبوات مغلقة
which were found after the peaceful revolution.
وجدت بعد الثورة السلمية.
For all these tasks, highly specialized departments
لكل هذه المهمات، تولت إدارات متخصصة
were responsible.
جدًا المسؤولية.
The one which was tapping phone calls
الشخص الذي تنصت على المكلمات
was completely separated
كان منفصلًا تماما
from the one which controlled the letters,
عن الذي تحكم بالرسائل،
for good reasons,
لأسباب جيدة،
because if one agent quit the Stasi,
لأنه إن استقال أحد العملاء من الستاسي
his knowledge was very small.
معرفته صغيرة جدًا.
Contrast that with Snowden, for example.
قارنوا ذلك بسنودن، على سبيل المثال.
But the vertical specialization was also important
ولكن التخصص العامودي كان هامًا أيضًا
to prevent all kinds of empathy
لمنع جميع أنواع التعاطف
with the object of observation.
مع الهدف المراقَب.
The agent who shadowed me
العميل الذي تبعني
didn't know who I was
لم يعلم من كنت
or why I was surveyed.
ولا لم كنت أراقب.
In fact, I smuggled forbidden books
في الواقع هرّبت كتبا ممنوعة
from West to East Germany.
من غرب لشرق ألمانيا.
But what was even more typical for the Stasi
ولكن ما كان أكثر اعتيادًا للستاسي
was the use of human intelligence,
كان استخدام الاستخبار البشري،
people who reported secretly to the Stasi.
أشخاص بلغوا سريًا للستاسي.
For the Minister of State Security,
لوزير أمن الدولة،
these so-called unofficial employees
هؤلاء المسمّون بموظفين غير رسميين
were the most important tools.
كانوا أهم الأدوات.
From 1975 on, nearly 200,000 people
منذ 1975، 20 ألف شخص تقريبًا
collaborated constantly with the Stasi,
تعاونوا باستمرار مع الستاسي،
more than one percent of the population.
أكثر من 1٪ من السكان.
And in a way, the minister was right,
وبطريقة، كان الوزير محقًا،
because technical instruments
لأن الآلات التقنية
can only register what people are doing,
تستطيع فقط أن تسجل ما يفعله الناس،
but agents and spies can also report
بينما يقدر العملاء والجواسيس التبليغ
what people are planning to do
أيضًا عما ينويه الناس
and what they are thinking.
وعم يفكرون فيه.
Therefore, the Stasi recruited so many informants.
لذلك، جندت الستاسي الكثير من العملاء.
The system of how to get them
نظام كيفية إحضارهم
and how to educate them, as it was called,
وكيفية تعليمهم، كما كانت تسمى،
was very sophisticated.
كانت معقدة جدًا.
The Stasi had its own university,
كان للستاسي جامعتها الخاصة،
not far away from here,
ليست بعيدة من هنا،
where the methods were explored
حيث كانت الطرق تستكشف
and taught to the officers.
وتعلم للضباط.
This guideline gave a detailed description
هذا التعليم أعطى وصفًا دقيقًا
of every step you have to take
لكل خطوة يجب اتخاذها
if you want to convince human beings
إن أردت إقناع بشر
to betray their fellow citizens.
لخيانة رفاقهم المواطنين.
Sometimes it's said that informants were pressured
أحيانًا يقال أن العملاء ضُغطوا
to becoming one,
ليصبحوا كذلك،
but that's mostly not true,
لكن أغلب هذا غير صحيح،
because a forced informant is a bad informant.
لأن عميلًا مغصوبًا هو عميل سيء.
Only someone who wants to give you the information you need
فقط شخص يريد إعطاءك المعلومات التي تحتاجها
is an effective whistleblower.
هو مبلّغ فعال.
The main reasons why people cooperated with the Stasi
السبب الرئيسي لتعاون الناس مع الستاسي
were political conviction and material benefits.
كانت القناعة السياسية والفوائد المادية.
The officers also tried to create a personal bond
الضباط حاولوا أيضًا تكوين رابط شخصي
between themselves and the informant,
بين نفسهم والعميل
and to be honest, the example of the Stasi shows
وبصراحة، مثال الستاسي يرينا
that it's not so difficult to win someone
أنه ليس من الصعب ضم شخص ما
in order to betray others.
لخيانة آخرين.
Even some of the top dissidents in East Germany
مع أن بعض أعلى المعارضين في ألمانيا الشرقية
collaborated with the Stasi,
تعاونوا مع الستاسي
as for instance Ibrahim Böhme.
كمثل إبراهيم بوهم.
In 1989, he was the leader of the peaceful revolution
في 1989 كان قائدة الثورة السلمية
and he nearly became the first freely elected Prime Minister of the GDR
وكاد أن يكون أول رئيس وزراء منتخب بحرية للـGDR
until it came out that he was an informant.
حتى انكشف أنه كان عميلا.
The net of spies was really broad.
شبكة الجواسيس كانت واسعة حقًا.
In nearly every institution,
في كل مؤسسة تقريبا
even in the churches or in West Germany,
حتى في الكنائس أو ألمانيا الغربية
there were many of them.
كان هناك الكثير منهم.
I remember telling a leading Stasi officer,
أذكر إخبار ضابط قائد في الستاسي،
"If you had sent an informant to me,
"إن أرسلتم عميلا لي
I would surely have recognized him."
كنت لأتعرف عليه بالتأكيد."
His answer was,
كانت إجابته
"We didn't send anyone.
"لم نرسل أحدًا.
We took those who were around you."
أخذنا من كان حولك."
And in fact, two of my best friends
في الحقيقة، اثنان من أعز أصحابي
reported about me to the Stasi.
بلغوا عني للستاسي.
Not only in my case, informers were very close.
لم يكن العملاء قريبين في حالتي فقط.
For example, Vera Lengsfeld, another leading dissident,
مثلًا، فيرا لنجزفيلد، قائدة معارضة أخرى،
in her case it was her husband who spied on her.
في حالتها كان زوجها من تجسس عليها.
A famous writer was betrayed by his brother.
كاتب مشهور خانه أخوه.
This reminds me of the novel "1984" by George Orwell,
يذكرني هذا برواية "1948" لجورج اورويل،
where the only apparently trustable person
حيث الشخص الوحيد الذي بدا موثوقًا به
was an informer.
كان عميلًا.
But why did the Stasi collect all this information
ولكن لماذا جمعت الستاسي كل هذه المعلومات
in its archives?
في سجلاتها؟
The main purpose was to control the society.
الهدف الرئيسي هو التحكم بالمجتمع.
In nearly every speech, the Stasi minister
في تقريبًا كل خطبة، أعطى وزير الستاسي
gave the order to find out who is who,
أمرًا بإيجاد من هو من
which meant who thinks what.
والذي يعني من يفكر بماذا.
He didn't want to wait until somebody
لم يرد الانتظار حتى
tried to act against the regime.
يحاول شخص الاعتداء على النظام.
He wanted to know in advance
كان يريد المعرفة مسبقًا
what people were thinking and planning.
بما يفكر الناس وما يخططون.
The East Germans knew, of course,
الألمان الشرقيون علموا، بالطبع،
that they were surrounded by informers,
أنهم كانوا محاطين بالعملاء،
in a totalitarian regime that created mistrust
في نظام شمولي ولّد انعدام الثقة
and a state of widespread fear,
وحالة من الخوف المتفشي،
the most important tools to oppress people
أهم الأدوات لقمع شعب
in any dictatorship.
في أي دكتاتورية.
That's why not many East Germans tried
لهذا لم يحاول الكثير من الألمان الشرقيين
to fight against the Communist regime.
مواجهة النظام الشيوعي.
If yes, the Stasi often used a method
إذا فعلوا، استخدم الستاسي عادة
which was really diabolic.
طريقة شيطانية فعلًا.
It was called Zersetzung,
كانت تسمى "التزيستزونج".
and it's described in another guideline.
وتوصف في وقت آخر.
The word is difficult to translate because it means
الكلمة تصعب ترجمتها لأنها تعني
originally "biodegradation."
في الأصل "التحلل الحيوي".
But actually, it's a quite accurate description.
لكن في الواقع، هذا وصف دقيق.
The goal was to destroy secretly
الهدف كان تدمير سريًا
the self-confidence of people,
ثقة الناس بأنفسهم،
for example by damaging their reputation,
مثلا عبر تشويه سمعتهم،
by organizing failures in their work,
عبر تنظيم إخفاقات في عملهم،
and by destroying their personal relationships.
وعبر تدمير علاقاتهم الخاصة.
Considering this, East Germany was a very modern dictatorship.
من هذا الاعتبار، كانت ألمانيا الشرقية دكتاتورية حديثة جدًا.
The Stasi didn't try to arrest every dissident.
لم تحاول الستاسي اعتقال كل معارض.
It preferred to paralyze them,
فضلت شلّهم،
and it could do so because
واستطاعت ذلك لأنه
it had access to so much personal information
كانت لديها الكثير من المعلومات الشخصية
and to so many institutions.
وقدرة على الوصول للعديد من المؤسسات.
Detaining someone was used only
احتجاز أحد ما كان يستعمل
as a last resort.
فقط كملاذ أخير.
For this, the Stasi owned 17 remand prisons,
لهذا، ملكت الستاسي 17 سجنًا مؤقت،
one in every district.
واحدًا في كل مقاطعة.
Here, the Stasi also developed
هنا، طورت الستاسي أيضًا
quite modern methods of detention.
طرقًا حديثة في الاحتجاز.
Normally, the interrogation officer
عادة، لم يعذب
didn't torture the prisoner.
ضابط الاستجواب السجين.
Instead, he used a sophisticated system
بدلًا من ذلك استخدم نظاما معقدا
of psychological pressure
من الضغط النفسي
in which strict isolation was central.
حيث العزل الكامل أمر جوهري.
Nearly no prisoner resisted
لم يقاوم تقريبًا أي سجين
without giving a testimony.
دون إعطاء شهادة.
If you have the occasion,
إن سنحت لك الفرصة،
do visit the former Stasi prison in Berlin
قم بزيارة السجن السابق للستاسي في برلين
and attend a guided tour with a former political prisoner
واحضر جولة إرشادية مع سجين سياسي سابق
who will explain to you how this worked.
سيشرح لك كيف عمل هذا.
One more question needs to be answered:
سؤال آخر يحتاج لإجابة:
If the Stasi were so well organized,
إن كانت الستاسي منظمة هكذا،
why did the Communist regime collapse?
لماذا سقط النظام الشيوعي؟
First, in 1989, the leadership in East Germany
أولا، في 1989، القيادة في ألمانيا الشرقية
was uncertain what to do against
لم تكن متأكدة عمّا تفعل
the growing protest of people.
ضد الاحتجاجات المتزايدة للناس.
It was especially confused
كانت مرتبكة خصوصًا
because in the mother country of socialism,
لأن في الدولة الأم للاشتراكية،
the Soviet Union,
الاتحاد السوفيتي،
a more liberal policy took place.
طبِّقت سياسة أكثر ليبرالية.
In addition, the regime was dependent
بالإضافة، كان النظام معتمدا
on the loans from the West.
على ديون من الغرب.
Therefore, no order to crash down the uprising
لذلك، لا أمر لإسقاط الثورة
was given to the Stasi.
أعطيَ للستاسي.
Secondly, in the Communist ideology,
ثانيا، في الفكر الشيوعي،
there's no place for criticism.
لا مكان للانتقاد.
Instead, the leadership stuck to the belief
عوضًا، تمسكت القيادة باعتقاد
that socialism is a perfect system,
أن الاشتراكية نظام كامل،
and the Stasi had to confirm that, of course.
والستاسي وجب عليها تأكيد ذلك، بالطبع.
The consequence was
النتيجة كانت أنه
that despite all the information,
رغم كل تلك المعلومات،
the regime couldn't analyze its real problems,
لم يستطع النظام تحليل مشاكله الحقيقية
and therefore it couldn't solve them.
ولذلك لم يستطع حلها.
In the end, the Stasi died
في النهاية ماتت الستاسي
because of the structures
بسبب البنية
that it was charged with protecting.
التي كلفت بحمايتها.
The ending of the Stasi
نهاية الستاسي
was something tragic,
كانت أمرًا مأساويا
because these officers
لأن هؤلاء الضباط
were kept busy during the peaceful revolution
تم إبقاؤهم منشغلين خلال الثورة السلمية
with only one thing:
بأمر واحد فقط:
to destroy the documents
تدمير الوثائق
they had produced during decades.
التي أصدروها خلال عقود.
Fortunately,
لحسن الحظ،
they had been stopped by human rights activists.
أوقفوا من قبل نشطاء حقوق إنسان.
That's why today we can use the files
لهذا نستطيع اليوم استخدام الملفات
to get a better understanding
للحصول على فهم أفضل
of how a surveillance state functions.
عن كيفية عمل دولة الرقابة.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you. Thank you very much.
برونو جويساني: شكرا. شكرا جزيلا لك.
So Hubertus, I want to ask you a couple of questions
حسنا هوبرتس، أريد سؤالك بضع أسئلة
because I have here Der Spiegel from last week.
لأنه لديه هنا "دير سبيجل" من الأسبوع الماضي.
"Mein Nachbar NSA." My neighbor, the NSA.
"ماين ناخبر NSA" جاري، الـNSA.
And you just told us about my neighbor,
وقد أخبرتنا توك عن جاري،
the spies and the informant from East Germany.
الجواسيس والعملاء من ألمانيا الشرقية.
So there is a direct link between these two stories
إذًا هناك علاقة مباشرة بين هاتين القصتين
or there isn't?
أليس كذلك؟
What's your reaction as a historian when you see this?
ما ردة فعلك كمؤرخ حين ترى هذا؟
Hubertus Knabe: I think there are
هوبرتس كنابي: أعتقد أن
several aspects to mention.
هناك عدة جوانب لذكرها.
At first, I think there's a difference
في البداية، أعتقد أن هناك فرقًا
of why you are collecting this data.
عن لماذا تجمعون هذه البيانات.
Are you doing that for protecting your people
هل تفعلون ذلك لحماية شعبكم
against terrorist attacks,
ضد الاعتداءات الإرهابية،
or are you doing that for oppressing your people?
أم لقمع الشعب؟
So that makes a fundamental difference.
هذا فرق أساسي.
But on the other hand,
من الناحية الأخرى،
also in a democracy, these instruments can be abused,
في ديمقراطية أيضًا، هذه الأدوات قد يسوء استعمالها،
and that is something where we really have
وهذا أمر علينا فعلًا
to be aware to stop that,
أن نعي لإيقافه،
and that also the intelligence services
وأيضًا أن الخدمات الاستخباراتية
are respecting the rules we have.
تحترم قواعدنا.
The third point, probably,
النقطة الثالثة، على الأغلب،
we really can be happy that we live in a democracy,
هو أنه يمكن كوننا سعداء لعيشنا في ديمقراطية
because you can be sure that Russia and China
لأنه يمكن أن تتيقن أن روسيا والصين
are doing the same,
يفعلون المثل،
but nobody speaks about that
لكن لا أحد يتحدث عن ذلك
because nobody could do that.
لأنه لا أحد يستطيع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BG: When the story came out first,
ب.ج.: حين خرجت القصة بدايةً،
last July, last year,
يونيو الماضي، العام الماضي
you filed a criminal complaint
رفعت شكوى جنائية
with a German tribunal. Why?
مع محكمة ألمانية. لماذا؟
HK: Yeah, I did so because of the second point I mentioned,
ه.ك.: نعم، قمت بذلك بسبب النقطة الثانية التي ذكرتها
that I think especially in a democracy,
بأني أعتقد أنه خصوصا أنّنا في ديمقراطية،
the rules are for everybody.
القواعد للجميع.
They are made for everybody, so it's not allowed
تم وضعها من أجل الجميع، لذا لا يسمح
that any institution doesn't respect the rules.
لأي مؤسسة ألا تحترم القواعد.
In the criminal code of Germany, it's written
في القانون الجنائي في ألمانيا، كتب
that it's not allowed to tap somebody
أنه غير مسموح التنصت على أحد
without the permission of the judge.
دون إذن قاضٍ.
Fortunately, it's written in the criminal code of Germany,
لحسن الحظ، كتب ذلك في القانون الجنائي الألماني،
so if it's not respected, then I think
لذا إن لم تحترم، أعتقد
an investigation is necessary,
أن التحقيق واجب،
and it took a very long time that
وأخذ وقت طويل جدًا
the public prosecutor of Germany started this,
حتى بدأ المدعي العام في ألمانيا هذا،
and he started it only in the case of Angela Merkel,
وبدأها فقط في حالة أنجيلا ميركل،
and not in the case of all the other people living in Germany.
وليس في حالة جميع من يعيش في ألمانيا.
BG: That doesn't surprise me because —
ب.ج.: هذا لا يفاجئني بسبب --
(Applause) —
(تصفيق) --
because of the story you told.
بسبب القصة التي أخبرتها.
Seen from the outside, I live outside of Germany,
نظرًا من الخارج، أعيش خارج ألمانيا،
and I expected the Germans to react
وتوقعت الألمان أن يردوا
much more strongly, immediately.
بقوة أكثر، مباشرة.
And instead, the reaction really came only
وعوضًا، أتت ردة الفعل فقط
when Chancellor Merkel was revealed
حين كشف أن أنجيلا ميركل
as being wiretapped. Why so?
كان يتنصت عليها. لماذا؟
HK: I take it as a good sign,
ه.ك.: آخذها كإشارة جيدة،
because people feel secure in this democracy.
لأن الناس يشعرون بأمان في هذه الديمقراطية.
They aren't afraid that they will be arrested,
لا يخافون الاعتقال،
and if you leave this hall after the conference,
وإن غادرت القاعة بعد هذا المؤتمر،
nobody has to be afraid that the secret police
لا يجب أن يخاف أحد أن الشرطة السرية
is standing out and is arresting you.
واقفة وستعتقلك.
So that's a good sign, I think.
لذلك هذه إشارة حسنة، أعتقد.
People are not really scared, as they could be.
الشعب ليس خائفًا كما يمكن أن يكونوا.
But of course, I think, the institutions
لكن بالطبع، أعتقد، أن المؤسسات
are responsible to stop illegal actions
مسؤولة عن وقف الأفعال الغير قانونية
in Germany or wherever they happen.
في ألمانيا أو أينما يحصلون.
BG: A personal question, and this is the last one.
ب.ج.: سؤال شخصي، وهذا هو الأخير.
There has been a debate in Germany about
كانت هناك مناظرة في ألمانيا حول
granting asylum to Edward Snowden.
منح اللجوء لإدوارد سنوودن.
Would you be in favor or against?
هل ستكون مع أو ضد ذلك؟
HK: Oh, that's a difficult question,
ه.ك.: أوه، هذا سؤال صعب،
but if you ask me,
لكن إن سألتني،
and if I answer honestly,
وإن جاوبت بصراحة،
I would give him the asylum,
سأمنحه حق اللجوء،
because I think it was really brave what he did,
لأني أعتقد أن ما فعله عمل شجاع،
and he destroyed his whole life
ودمر حياته بأكملها
and his family and everything.
وعائلته وكل شيء
So I think, for these people, we should do something,
لذا أعتقد، لهؤلاء، يجب فعل شيء ما،
and especially if you see the German history,
خصوصا إن رأيت تاريخ ألمانيا،
where so many people had to escape
حيث احتاج الكثير من الناس الهروب
and they asked for asylum in other countries
وطلبوا اللجوء في دول أخرى
and they didn't get it,
ولم يحصلوا عليه،
so it would be a good sign to give him asylum.
لذا ستكون إشارة طيبة أن يمنح اللجوء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BG: Hubertus, thank you very much.
ب.ج.: هوبرتس، شكرا جزيلا لك.